A Guide to The Peter Family Papers, ca. 1700-1897 and n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
The Peter Family Papers ca. 1700-1897 and n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7605-a
This collection consists of ca. 181 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Scope and Content Information
Include papers, land deeds and surveys, 1696-1803, pertaining to Robert Peter's property in Maryland and Washington, D.C., including a 1743 land grant signed by Charles Calvert; papers and letterbook, 1790- 1803, of Robert Peter, concerning tobacco and land sales and legal matters; and papers, 1798-1812, pertaining to the estate of Robert Peter, including copies, 1798-1805, of his will and a legal opinion of Francis Scott Key.
Also include accounts and receipts, 1800-1831, pertaining to Martha Washington's estate; accounts, 1802, of George Washington Parke Custis; and a survey, n.d., of "Woodstock" for the heirs of George Washington.
Also include military records, orders, reports, and papers, 1801-1814, of George Peter; letters, 1801-1809, from James A. Wilkinson to George Peter, with one to Zebulon Pike, concerning military orders, duties and discipline, the exploration of the Missouri river, and plans to go to New Orleans; and a subpoena, 1810, summoning George Peter, re: the Burr-Wilkinson conspiracy.
Also include letters, 1808-1813, to George Peter concerning an officer's dislike of his re-assignment to Detroit, military life, and two marches, with sheet music, composed for his company; letter, 1814, from Francis Scott Key re: Peter's choice of position and Key's suggestions prior to Battle of Bladensburg; papers, 1816-17, concerning military service and a pension for disabled veteran of the War of 1812.
Also include documents, ca. 1814, pertaining to the trial of Archibald Lee, an alleged British spy at the Battle of Bladensburg; and papers, correspondence, and printed materials, 1825-1838, concerning effects of the accusations on Lee's later political candidacy and his libel suit against George Peter.
Also include papers, land records, accounts and receipts, 1807-1856, of George Peter concerning business interests, legal matters, estate settlements, plans to sell slaves in Georgetown (1936), current slave market (1850), and fugitive slaves escaping to Pennsylvania; and wills and estate records, 1806-1828, of Peter family members.
Also include miscellaneous family letters, 1836-1885; letter, 1897, from the Nevius Company requesting permission to reproduce George Washington's mirror; and letter, n.d., from S. Weir Mitchell with medical advice to give up tobacco.
Also include letters, 1814-1857, from various Maryland politicians, including Francis Scott Key, to George Peter pertaining political appointments and congressional nominations; letter, 1816, Augustus Taney re: political attack on Taney and brother; and letter, 1818, from Roger Brooke Taney re: current legislation and financial difficulties of Maryland.
Also include Beverley Kennon's naval commission, 1837; and documents, 1843, pertaining to his purchase of a house in Washington, D.C.
Also include letters, 1862-1863, from Walter Gibson Peter, with the Army of Tennessee, to his sister, concerning family matters, military life, estimation of army strength, anticipation of Rosecrans' movements, and a comparison of Army of Tennessee with Army of Northern Virginia; and letter, 1863, from Charles H. Nourse to Walter Gibson Peter re: news of relative drafted by Union who would prefer to fight with Confederacy and joining the Signal Corps.
Also include letter, 1863, William Orton Williams (aka Lawrence W. Orton) to his sister denying he is a spy; and biographical information on Walter Gibson Peter and William Orton Williams.
Ephemera includes bill of lading, 1790; Gibb family genealogical records; images (various processes) of the Scott family, a servant, and furnishings from Mount Vernon; and other miscellany.
Contents List
- Land Grant: unidentified ca. 1700, AD (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous Survey Records 1728-1762, ca. 19 items (Box 1)
- Charles Calvert: Land Grant to Benjamin Young and George Scott 1743, ADS (Box 1)
- Act of Maryland Council Concerning Bradford Surgeon Land Dispute 1748, ADS (Box 1)
- Table of Monetary Values 1751, 1 item (Box 1)
- Survey of "Fortune," Prince George's County, Md. for Robert Peter 1760 October 2[9], 1 item (Box 1)
- Survey Corrections: Lands of Henry Hall and David Stoner 1761-1774, 1 item (Box 1)
- Land Grant to Robert Peter 1762 September 29, ADS (Box 1)
- John Wofford: Land Grant 1764 March 1, ADS (Box 1)
- Richard Henderson: Land Patent 1764, ADS (Box 1)
- William Williams: Land Grant 1766, ADS (Box 1)
- Re-Survey of Land at Sugar Bottom 1768 April 13, ADS (Box 1)
- Robert Peter: Land Grant 1768, ADS (Box 1)
- S. Newton Chiswell: Partnership Agreement on Indenture 1768, ADS (Box 1)
- Robert Peter: Indentures and Contracts 1768-1800, 6 items (Box 1)
- Land Survey: not identified 1769 October 18, ADS (Box 1)
- Re-Survey of "Brandy" Tract 1769 October 18, ADS (Box 1)
- Robert Eden, Deed for "Good Luck" to William Douglass 1770 June 7, ADS (Box 1)
- Robert Peter: Land Grant 1770 October 17, ADS (Box 1)
- Form of Indenture between Angus McDonald and Robert Peter 1770, ADS (Box 1)
- Maryland Colonial Currency 1770-1774, 14 items (Box 1)
- Joseph Stallings: Bill of Land Sale 1771, ADS (Box 1)
- Robert Peter: Land Patent 1772, ADS (Box 1)
- Robert Peter: Misc. deeds 1772-1801, 4 items (Box 1)
- Form of Indenture between Robert Peter and Adam Stewart 1773, ADS (Box 1)
- Pennsylvania Colonial Currency 1773, 3 items (Box 1)
- Survey Records 1775-1800, 9 items (Box 1)
- U.S. Continental Currency 1776-1777, 2 items (Box 1)
- Estate of Angus McDonald post 1778, AD (Box 1)
- Deeds of William Deakins 1780 and 1793, 2 ADS (Box 1)
- Robert Peter: Deed to "No. 10" 1783 March 14, ADS (Box 1)
- Re-Survey of "Double Distilled Brandy" 1784 June 12, ADS (Box 1)
- William Smith: Re-Survey order 1789 October 27, ALS (Box 1)
- William Smith to Robert Peter 1790 May 24, ADS (Box 1)
- George Scott: Receipt to Robert Peter 1791 March 28, ADS (Box 2)
- Robert Peter: Land Grant 1791 October 1, ADS (Box 2)
- Form of Indenture between Basil West and Robert Peter 1792, ADS (Box 2)
- State of Md. Re-Survey warrant to Zachariah Ellis 1793 May 22, ADS (Box 2)
- Letterbook: Robert Peter 1794-1796, 1 item (Box 2)
- Philip B. Key to Robert Peter 1795 May 9, ALS (Box 2)
- List of lands & property of Robert Peter 1796 January 1, 1 item (Box 2)
- Robert Peter Indenture with William Hanson McPherson 1797 September 11, ADS (Box 2)
- Bill of Sale: Neale Maguines to Robert Peter 1797 November 17, ADS (Box 2)
- Estate of Robert Peter 1798-1811, 14 items (Box 2)
- Deed for "Good Luck" and "Good Luck Again" for Robert Peter 1799 July 12, ADS (Box 2)
- Form of indenture between Robert Peter and Adam Whann 1799, ADS (Box 2)
- Printed form for Declaration of Shipment 179[?], D (Box 2)
- Thomas Peter: Deed of Sale to Robert Peter 1800 April 28, ADS (Box 2)
- Robert Peter: Land Grant 1800 November 11, ADS (Box 2)
- Survey Records ca. 1800, 5 items (Box 2)
- Estate of Martha Washington 1800-1831, 34 items (Box 2)
- George Peter: Commission as Lieutenant 1801 February 18, ADS (Box 2)
- James A. Wilkinson to George Peter 1801 March 19, ALS (Box 2)
- George Peter: Commission as Lieutenant, signed by Thomas Jefferson and Henry Dearborn 1802 April 17, ADS (Box 2)
- George Washington Parke Curtis: Accounts 1802, 3 items (Box 2)
- Thomas Peter: Business Papers 1802-1822, 4 items (Box 2)
- Robert Peter: Land Patent 1803 March 4, ADS (Box 2)
- Denton Jacques to Robert Peter 1803 August 2, ALS (Box 2)
- James A. Wilkinson to George Peter 1805 April 19, ALS (Box 2)
- James A. Wilkinson to George Peter 1805 August 6, ALS (Box 2)
- James A. Wilkinson to George Peter 1806 March 3, ALS (Box 2)
- James A. Wilkinson to George Peter 1806 June 26, ALS (Box 2)
- James A. Wilkinson to George Peter 1806 June 28, ALS (Box 2)
- Copy of a letter, James Hill (Glasgow) to Robert Peter concerning death and estate of Alexander Peter 1806 July 21, ALS (Box 2)
- Benjamin Wilkinson to George Peter 1806 September 26, ALS. Docketed "General Wilkinson" (Box 2)
- Robert Peter: Will 1807 April 7, ADS (Box 2)
- U.S. Arsenal on Schuykill: Inventory of Stores deliverable to George Peter at Fort McHenry 1807 November 24, AD (Box 2)
- George Peter: Accounts and receipts 1807-1828, 7 items (Box 2)
- James Wilkinson to Lt. Pike 1808 May 30, ALS (Box 2)
- James A. Wilkinson to George Peter 1808 June 18, ALS (Box 2)
- John Holmes to Thomas Duncan, presenting George Peter 1808 August 15, ALS (Box 2)
- James A. Wilkinson to George Peter 1809 January 2, ALS (Box 2)
- [?] to George Peter 1809 September 3, ALS (Box 2)
- Receipt: Union Bank of Georgetown to George Peter 1809 December 6, 1 item (Box 2)
- Printed Booklet: Union Bank of Georgetown1809, 1 item (Box 2)
- Peter Family Banking Record 1809-1810, 1 item (Box 3)
- George Peter: Military Reports and Accounts 1809-1814, 5 items (Box 3)
- Check: George Peter Against Union Bank of Georgetown 1810 November 13, 1 item (Box 3)
- Subpoena: summoning George Peter to appear before special committee of U.S. House of Representatives investigating Bun-Wilkinson Conspiracy 1810 December 9, DS (Box 3)
- Record of Estate of Robert Peter, Jr. 1810, Bound vol. (Box 3)
- George Peter: Misc. checks 1810-1811, 22 items (Box 3)
- re. military service of James Gibson 1810-1816, 6 items (Box 3)
- George Peter: Misc. notes & checks 1810-1850, 9 items (Box 3)
- Check: George Peter to Charles Hill, against Union Bank of Georgetown 1811 February 27, 1 item (Box 3)
- Legal Notes of William Smith, with signed opinion of Francis Scott Key 1812 April 24 & 25, 4 ll. (Box 3)
- Holograph copy of David Peter will 1812 November 30, DS (Box 3)
- George Peter Land Records 1812-1825, 12 items (Box 3)
- John Morton to Major Peter re. conduct of war 1813 August 13, ALS (Box 3)
- P. L. Duport to George Peter with sheet music 1813 September 15, ALS (Box 3)
- Estate of David Peter 1813-1825, 2 items (Box 3)
- D. Wadsworth: order to commanding officer of troops at Benedick 1814 June 22, ALS (Box 3)
- Field dispatch to Major Peter 1814 June 23, 1 item (Box 3)
- George Peter: military orders 1814 June 23 & n.d., 2 items (Box 3)
- Francis Scott Key to Major George Peter 1814 October 17, ALS (Box 3)
- ALS to George Peter and 3 items re. War of 1812, British spies, and Col. Munroe ca. 1812, 4 items (Box 3)
- Political letters to George Peter 1814-1824, 7 ALS (Box 3)
- Augustus Taney to George Peter 1816 August 16, ALS (Box 3)
- Ninian Pinckney to George Peter 1816 November 18, ALS (Box 3)
- "Rights of Montgomery and Federalism of the Washington School Sustained" 1816, printed booklet (Box 3)
- Stock certificates of George Peter for Georgetown & Leesburg Turnpike Co. 1817 August 20, 2 DS (Box 3)
- to George Peter re. pension for veteran of War of 1812 1817 December 31, ALS (Box 3)
- R. B. Taney to George Peter 1818 December 26, ALS (Box 3)
- George Peter: Misc. Business Correspondence 1818-1837, 5 items (Box 3)
- Memorandum Book 1820-1822, bound vol. (Box 3)
- Survey of "Conclusion," etc. 1823 June 12, 2 items (Box 3)
- H. Howard to George Peter 1824 January 30, ALS (Box 3)
- William Cook to George Peter 1824 February 23, ALS (Box 3)
- Samuel Barnes to George Peter 1824 July 29, ALS (Box 3)
- Henry Baker to George Peter 1824 October 22, ALS (Box 3)
- B. S. Forrest to George Peter with trial transcript 1825 April 25, ALS (Box 3)
- Sarah Freeland: will [ re. James and Robert Peter] 1828 August 19, 1 item (Box 3)
- Samuel Harrison Smith to George Peter 1829 October 2, ALS (Box 3)
- Archibald Lee to George Peter 1830 June 23, ALS (Box 3)
- "To the Voters of Montgomery County" 1830 September 27, broadside (Box 3)
- "To the Independent Voters of Montgomery County" 1830 September 30, broadside (Box 3)
- "To the Voters of Montgomery County" (one with autograph marginalia) 1830, broadside (2 copies) (Box 3)
- "To the Patriotic Voters of Montgomery County" 1830, broadside (Box 3)
- "To the Voters of Montgomery County" with autograph marginalia 1830, broadside (Box 3)
- Receipts: George Peter ca. 1830-1850, ca. 150 items (Box 3)
- William W. Thompson to George Peter 1832 March 16, ALS (Box 3)
- Robert Peter: School Receipt 1836 December 5, 1 item (Box 3)
- James Dunlop to George Peter 1836-1845, 8 ALS (Box 4)
- James F. Peter to George Peter 1836-1849, 2 ALS (Box 4)
- Beverly Kennon: Commission as Captain, USN, signed by Andrew Jackson and Mahlon Dickerson 1837 March 3, ADS (Box 4)
- Form letter, M. Dickerson to Beverly Kennon: notification of appointment as Captain 1837 March 6, ALS (Box 4)
- Archibald Lee: Legal Papers 1838, 2 p (Box 4)
- Robert Dunlop to George Peter 1839, ALS (Box 4)
- Brice Selby to John Peter 1841 July 23, ALS (Box 4)
- Jane A. Cooper to Beverly Kennon 1843 March 26, ALS (Box 4)
- Beverly Kennon: DS concerning purchase of house in Washington, D. C., from G. C. Cooper 1843, ca. 15 items. (Box 4)
- George Peter: miscellaneous correspondence 1845-1856, 4 ALS (Box 4)
- "Taylor Meeting," 2 copies 1848 March 6, broadside (Box 4)
- Subscription tickets to The Buena Vista printed together as a broadsheet 1848, 1 item (Box 4)
- [?] to General Taylor re. election [copy?] 1849 April 27, ALS (Box 4)
- John N. Denning to L. W. Candler 1850 January 10, ALS (Box 4)
- Philip F. Thurman to George Peter 1850 September 24, ALS (Box 4)
- J. T. Higgins to George Peter 1850 October 10, ALS (Box 4)
- Uriah Forest to George Peter 1850, ALS (Box 4)
- Sallie [?] to George Peter 1851, ALS (Box 4)
- Leon W. Candler to George Peter 1851-1853, 2 ALS (Box 4)
- Political letters to George Peter 1854-1857, 6 ALS (Box 4)
- Robert P. Dodge to George Peter 1855 August 6, ALS (Box 4)
- George Peter: Commission as Commissioner of Public Works for the 2nd [Md.] district 1855 November 22, DS (Box 4)
- Leon W. Candler to [?] 1856 December 20, ALS (Box 4)
- Sealon to Major Peters 1857 January 8, ALS (Box 4)
- Leon W. Candler to [?] 1857 January 15, ALS (Box 4)
- William Veirs to George Peter 1857 August 26, ALS (Box 4)
- Peter Family: Civil War Letters and two transcripts 1862-1863, 8 items (Box 4)
- Poem 1864 November 5, AMs (Box 4)
- Mrs. Armistead Peter to Armistead Peter 1870-1885, 8 ALS (Box 4)
- Armistead Peter: Confirmation Certificate 1872 April 14, D (Box 4)
- William A. [?] to Armistead Peter re. military service of George Peter 1884, 3 items (Box 4)
- Armistead Peter to Mrs. Armistead Peter 1885, 2 ALS (Box 4)
- The Nevius Co. to Mrs. Brittania Kennon re. Washington mirror from Mt. Vernon 1897 July 12, TLS (Box 4)
- James A. Wilkinson to George Peter n.d., ALS (Box 4)
- James Wilkinson to George Peter n.d., ALS (Box 4)
- John Candler to George Peter n.d., ALS (Box 4)
- Denton Jacques to Robert Peter n.d., ALS (Box 4)
- Nicholas [?] to John Peter n.d., ALS (Box 4)
- Eliza Peter to George Peter n.d., ALS (Box 4)
- Note to George Freeland from his grandmother n.d., Ms (Box 4)
- Francis Scott Key to George Peter n.d., ALS (Box 4)
- S. Weir to Armistead Peter n.d., ALS (Box 4)
- Unidentified notes re political and military affairs in Washington, Baltimore, New Market, etc. n.d., Ms (Box 4)
- Unidentified notes n.d., Ms (Box 4)
- George Peter: Acc'ts and Receipts n.d., 5 items (Box 4)
- List of voters n.d., 1 item (Box 4)
- Armistead Peter: Unidentified fragments n.d., 2 items (Box 4)
- Survey of "Woodstock": Heirs of George Washington n.d., AD (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous legal notes, etc. n.d. [ ca. 1790?], 3 items (Box 4)
- Gibb family Bible records n.d., 2 items (Box 4)
- Printed: 2 bond volumes and 3 speeches, printed n.d., 5 items (Box 4)
- "List of Committees of the House of Representatives" n.d., broadside (Box 4)
- "To the Federalists of Montgomery County" n.d., broadside (Box 4)
- Ticket to the Lafayette Dinner: Society of Cincinnati n.d., 1 item (Box 4)
- clippings n.d., 3 items (Box 4)
- "Drawing-Teacher" n.d. [ ca. 1850], photograph (Box 4)
- Furnishings from Mt. Vernon n.d., 3 photographs (Box 4)
- William Scott Family: 8 drawings, 2 photographs, 1 tintype n.d., 11 items (Box 4)
- wrappers n.d., ca. 10 items (Box 4)
- List of some of this group of papers [#7605-a] by G. Freeland Peter Jr. 1959 June 2, 1 item (Box 4)